<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.3//EN" "http://docbook.org/xml/4.3/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter id="lesson8">
  <title>Playing Music and Videos</title>
  
  <itemizedlist> 
    <title>Objectives</title>

	<para>In this lesson, you will learn to:</para>
         <listitem>
          <para>Play, edit and organize music and video files.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist> 
      <note userlevel="instructor">
        <title>Instructor Notes:</title>

        <para><emphasis role="italic">It is recommended to cover all the
        topics in this lesson. However,if you fall short of time then cover
        only the following topics:</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis role="italic">Legal Restrictions</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis role="italic">Playing Audio Files</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis role="italic">Viewing DVDs</emphasis></para>

        <para><emphasis role="italic">Playing Online Media</emphasis></para>
      </note>

  <sect1>
    <title>Legal Restrictions</title>

    <para>Ubuntu fully supports playback of music, videos and DVDs available
    in free and unrestricted formats. A number of multimedia formats are
    restricted by licenses and software patents in some jurisdictions. Ubuntu
    does not offer this capability by default for these formats but it easy
    to enable playing a variety of proprietary formats. This section will guide you
    through the patent and copyright restriction considerations for using
    proprietary file formats.</para>

    <para>The license of the format is different from the license of the
    content itself. For example a video's content can be licensed under a
    Creative Commons license, and be available as MPEG file. While the content
    can be distributed freely, the format is proprietary and a software for
    playback may need to be licensed in some jurisdictions.</para>

    <para>To understand the legal issues associated with the use of
    proprietary formats, you first need to understand the difference between free
    and non-free or proprietary formats.</para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Playing Music Files</title>

    <para>Ubuntu comes with the Rhythmbox Music Player to play and organise
    music files. Similar to iTunes in its interface, this music player is a
    free software application designed to work in the GNOME desktop
    environment. Using Rhythmbox, you can play your music files, listen to
    Internet radio, import music from CDs and organise your music files.
    Rhythmbox offers comprehensive audio support for a large number of audio
    formats and contains various useful features that make playing music easy
    and enjoyable.</para>

    <note userlevel="instructor">
      <title>Instructor Notes:</title>

      <para>You need to demonstrate and let the students play fully with at least
      1 music, 1 DVD playback and 1 audio recording.</para>
    </note>

    <sect2>
      <title>Playing Music using Rhythmbox</title>

      <procedure>
        <title>To play music using Rhythmbox:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Application</emphasis> menu,
          point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and
          then click <emphasis role="strong">Rhythmbox Music
          Player</emphasis>. A welcome screen is displayed.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Launching Rhythmbox</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_001.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The main window of the Rhythmbox Music Player opens. Now, you
          will be able to organise your favourite music using this
          window.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Rhythmbox Music Player</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_002.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>To start playing music in Rhythmbox, you need to first select
          the music source from the <emphasis role="strong">Source</emphasis>
          list. By default <emphasis role="strong">Library</emphasis> is
          selected as the source when you open Rhythmbox for the first
          time.</para>

          <para>Library is the main source available in Rhythmbox. You can
          import all your music files into the Rhythmbox library and can start
          playing immediately. You also use the music files in your library to
          create smart customised playlists and play-queues. To start
          importing individual music files, right-click <emphasis
          role="strong">Music</emphasis> and click <emphasis
          role="strong">Import File</emphasis>. It displays the <emphasis
          role="strong">Import File into Library</emphasis> dialogue
          box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Importing Music Files</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_003.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Import File into
          Library</emphasis> dialogue box, navigate to the folder from which
          you want to import the files. Select the files that you want to
          import and click <emphasis role="strong">Open</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting the Files to Import</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_004.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <tip>
            <title>Nice to Know:</title>

            <para>While importing music files from your music collection,
            Rhythmbox also imports the metadata tags associated with the
            files. These tags are used by Rhythmbox to categorise the music
            files by genre, artist, album, title, and track number.</para>
          </tip>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The selected music files are imported into the library and
          displayed in the the Rhythmbox window. You will notice that the main
          Rhythmbox window is split into various panes. Each pane displays
          different details about your music collection. To play music from
          the library, you can use the <emphasis role="strong">Artist,
          Album</emphasis> and <emphasis role="strong">Track</emphasis> panes
          to select the music tracks that you want to play and then use the
          playback controls to start playing the music tracks. Click the
          <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis> button to start playing the
          selected track.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Rhythmbox Window</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_005.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>If you click the <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis>
          button without selecting any track, Rhythmbox will start playing the
          first track from your current view. You can use the <emphasis
          role="strong">Shuffle</emphasis> button to play tracks randomly. You
          can also create a play list by right-clicking a music track and
          selecting <emphasis role="strong">Add to Playlist</emphasis>. To
          stop or pause a track, click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Play</emphasis> button again.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Creating New Playlist</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_006.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Rhythmbox offers many additional useful features in the form
          of various plugins. Some of these plugins are not turned on by
          default. To access these plugins, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">Edit</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Plugins.</emphasis> The <emphasis
          role="strong">Configure Plugins</emphasis> dialogue box
          opens.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Accessing Plugins</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_007.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can view all the available plugins in the left pane of the
          <emphasis role="strong">Configure Plugins</emphasis> dialogue box.
          Selecting a plugin displays its details in the right pane of the
          dialogue box.</para>

        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Depending on your requirements and preferences, you can
          activate these plugins to get extra functionality in your Rhythmbox.
          For example, the <emphasis role="strong">Magnatune
          Store</emphasis> plugin enables iTunes-style song previews and paid
          downloads. Activating <emphasis
          role="strong">Visualization</emphasis> renders a real-time
          visualization of the music on the screen while you listen to a song
          track. Similarly, if you want to automatically retrieve the lyrics
          of the song being played, activate <emphasis role="strong">Song
          Lyrics</emphasis> by selecting the corresponding check box and click
          <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the <emphasis
          role="strong">Configure Plugins</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Activating Plugins</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_008.png"
                           format="PNG" vendor="" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You are returned to the main Rhythmbox interface. To start
          retrieving the song lyrics, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">View</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Song Lyrics</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Retrieving Song Lyrics</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_009.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Amazingly, Rhythmbox retrieves the song lyrics for you. Now,
          you can sing along while listening to your favourite song.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Song Lyrics Retrieved</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_010.png"
                           format="PNG" width="8cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Similarly, if you wish to view animations while listening to a
          song, click the <emphasis role="strong"> Visualization</emphasis>
          button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Activating Visualisation</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_011.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can view animations while playing a song.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Viewing Animations</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_012.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Rhythmbox also enables you to listen to music from a variety
          of sources, such as Internet radio stations and podcasts.</para>

          <para>To play music from a podcast of your choice, right-click the
          <emphasis role="strong">Podcast</emphasis> option in the <emphasis
          role="strong">Library</emphasis> list and select <emphasis
          role="strong">New Podcast Feed</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Adding New Podcast Feed</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_013.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <note>
            <title>Note:</title>

            <para>Podcasts are audio shows broadcast over the Internet that
            you can subscribe to. Subscribing to a podcast enables you to
            download each new audio release from the subscribed podcast
            source.</para>
          </note>

          <note userlevel="instructor">
            <title>Instructor Notes:</title>

            <para>If the students want to know more about podcasts, advise
            them to read the Wikipedia article on podcasting: <ulink
            url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podcasting">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Podcasting</ulink>.</para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Enter the podcast feed URL in the <emphasis role="strong">New
          Podcast Feed</emphasis> text box and click <emphasis
          role="strong">Add</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Entering Podcast Feed URL</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_014.png"
                           format="PNG" width="9cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Rhythmbox automatically looks for the latest podcasts and
          downloads them for you. To play a podcast episode, select the
          episode that you want to play and click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Play</emphasis> button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing a Podcast</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_015.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Rhythmbox also allows you to listen to radio streamed from
          Internet radio stations across the world. To listen to Internet
          radio, click the <emphasis role="strong">Radio</emphasis> source in
          the <emphasis role="strong">Library</emphasis> pane.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing Internet Radio</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_016.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>By default the <emphasis role="strong">Radio</emphasis> source
          lists several radio stations, each of them broadcasting a different
          genre of music. Double-click on the radio station of your choice to
          listen to the streaming media.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Listening to a Radio Station</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_017.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <note userlevel="instructor">
            <title>Instructor Notes:</title>

            <para>Advise students to read the Wikipedia article on Internet
            Radio if they want more background information: <ulink
            url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_radio">http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_radio</ulink>.</para>
          </note>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can also add a new radio station to the existing list by
          clicking <emphasis role="strong">New Internet Radio
          Station</emphasis> and pasting the URL of the new radio station in
          the <emphasis role="strong">URL of Internet radio station</emphasis>
          text box. Click <emphasis role="strong">Add</emphasis> to add the
          radio station in the existing list.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Adding New Radio Station</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_018.png"
                           format="PNG" width="11cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can add many more Internet radio stations in the same way
          and listen to your favourite radio stations with just a click of
          your mouse.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Playing and Extracting Audio CDs</title>

    <para>Sound Juicer is the default application available in Ubuntu for
    playing and extracting audio compact discs (CDs). It is an easy-to-use CD
    player and ripping tool that requires minimal user intervention in playing
    and extracting audio CDs. Using Sound Juicer, you can play audio tracks
    directly from the CD and extract audio tracks and convert them into audio
    files. Sound Juicer allows you to extract audio files into the following
    three formats: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Ogg Vorbis: Ogg vorbis is a free, unpatented and open source
          alternative to the proprietary MP3 format. Like the MP3 format, it
          discards parts of the sound that humans cannot normally hear. An Ogg
          Vorbis file is typically a tenth of the size of a WAV format file
          containing the same content.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>FLAC: FLAC stands for Free Lossless Audio Codec. It is an
          unpatented, open source audio format. Unlike MP3 or Ogg Vorbis, FLAC
          compresses audio without discarding any information. A FLAC file is
          typically half the size of a WAV file containing the same
          content.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>WAV: WAV is short for Waveform Audio Format. It is an
          uncompressed format typically used for short snippets of sound and
          voice recordings.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>

    <note>
      <title>Note:</title>

      <para>To know more about Ogg Vorbis and FLAC audio format, visit the
      following Web sites: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://www.vorbis.com/faq/">http://www.vorbis.com/faq/</ulink></para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para><ulink
            url="http://flac.sourceforge.net/">http://flac.sourceforge.net/</ulink></para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>
    </note>

    <sect2>
      <title>Playing Audio CDs</title>

      <procedure>
        <title>To play audio CDs using Sound Juicer</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Insert an audio CD in the CD drive of your computer. The Sound
          Juicer CD player and ripper is launched automatically. To start
          Sound Juicer manually, click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu, point to <emphasis
          role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and then click <emphasis
          role="strong">Audio CD Extractor</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Launching Sound Juicer</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_019.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Sound Juicer's main interface is displayed. When Sound Juicer
          detects a CD, it examines the CD and tries to search the Internet to
          locate information about the CD's content. If you are connected to
          the Internet, Sound Juicer will retrieve the CD artist, title, and
          track data from MusicBrainz.org.</para>

          <para>To play all the tracks sequentially, you can simply click the
          <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis> button.</para>

          <note>
            <title>Note:</title>

            <para>MusicBrainz.org is a community-maintained online database,
            which contains data on over 360,000 published albums.</para>
          </note>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing Audio CD</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_020.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>Notice that Sound Juicer has fetched the track information
          from MusicBrainz.org. In the upper part of the Sound Juicer window,
          you can see the basic information about the disc, including title,
          artist, genre and total duration. The lower part of the window
          displays a list of tracks, each with its full title, artist and
          duration.</para>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>To play only the tracks of your choice, select the particular
          tracks by selecting the corresponding checkboxes and then click the
          <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis> button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting the Song tracks</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_021.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can now enjoy listening to your favourite music
          tracks.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing the Selected Tracks</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_022.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Extracting Audio CDs</title>

      <para>If you want to listen to your favourite music tracks without
      needing to insert a CD every time, you can create a copy of the CD and
      extract the music tracks on your computer.</para>

      <procedure>
        <title>To extract the audio CD:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Insert the audio CD and click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Extract</emphasis> button. However, if you want to
          define the audio quality, format and the location where the files
          would be stored, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> on the <emphasis
          role="strong">Edit</emphasis> menu. This displays the <emphasis
          role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Defining Preferences For Audio Files</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_023.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can use the <emphasis role="strong">Preferences</emphasis>
          dialogue box to define a number of things such as how the folder
          hierarchy should be saved, how the files should be named and whether
          to eject the CD automatically after the tracks are extracted.</para>

          <para>In the last section of the <emphasis
          role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue box, you can define
          the file format in which the tracks would be stored on your
          computer. Based on your requirements, select any one format from the
          <emphasis role="strong">Output Format</emphasis> drop-down
          list.</para>

          <tip>
            <title>Nice to Know:</title>

            <para>You can also extract CD audio files to the proprietary,
            non-free MP3 format. Instructions for extracting audio files into
            the MP3 format can be found in the help for Sound Juicer. Go to
            <emphasis role="strong">Help&gt;Content</emphasis> and then
            navigate to the Preferences section.</para>
          </tip>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Specifying Audio Format</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_024.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Each of these file format has its own customisable profile.
          Depending on the type of the music track and the destination where
          it has to be stored, you may need to customise these file formats.
          Click the <emphasis role="strong">Edit Profiles</emphasis> button,
          then select the desired profile and click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Edit</emphasis> button to edit the profile of the
          selected file format according to your needs.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Editing Audio Profile</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_025.png"
                           format="PNG" width="8cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The <emphasis role="strong">Editing profile</emphasis>
          dialogue box for the selected audio profile is displayed. You can
          edit the audio profile according to your requirements and the click
          <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Customising Audio Profile</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_026.png"
                           format="PNG" width="9cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can also use the <emphasis
          role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue box to define the
          location where you want the audio files to be stored on your
          computer. By default, Sound Juicer stores the audio files in the
          Home directory. To define a location of your choice, select a
          directory from the <emphasis role="strong">Music Folder</emphasis>
          drop-down list and click <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to
          exit the <emphasis role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue
          box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Specifying Audio File Location</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_027.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>After configuring your preferences, you can go ahead and start
          extracting all the tracks by clicking the <emphasis
          role="strong">Extract</emphasis> button. However, if you want to
          exclude some tracks, deselect them by clearing the corresponding
          check boxes.</para>

          <para>Depending on the speed of your computer, the extracting
          process can take a long time. You can watch the total progress of
          the process in the lower left section of the <emphasis
          role="strong">Sound Juicer</emphasis> window.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Extracting Song Tracks</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_028.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The CD audio tracks are now copied as audio files on your hard
          disk. You can listen to these tracks by simply double-clicking
          them.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Copied Tracks</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_030.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Burning Audio CDs</title>

    <para>Besides copying audio tracks from a CD to your computer, Ubuntu also
    enables you to copy music files from your computer onto a CD or DVD. Brasero
    is the CD/DVD burner application that comes bundled with Ubuntu, by
    default. It is an easy-to-use application that also allows CD/DVD data disc creation,
    CD/DVD copying and burning of existing images to CD/DVD.</para>

    <procedure>
      <title>To burn an audio CD:</title>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Launch Brasero by selecting the <emphasis role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu,
        point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and then
        click <emphasis role="strong">Brasero Disc Burning</emphasis>.
        The Brasero window is displayed.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Launching Brasero</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_032.png" format="PNG"
                         width="12cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The <emphasis role="strong">Brasero Window</emphasis>
        displays. Click the <emphasis role="strong">Audio Project</emphasis>
        button. You will need to navigate to the folder containing the audio tracks
        you wish to add to the new CD project.</para>
    
        <figure float="0">
          <title>The main window of Brasero</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_034.png" format="PNG"
                         width="15cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Now you need to specify the files that you want to be copied onto
        the blank CD. To start specifying the desired audio files, click the
        <emphasis role="strong">Music</emphasis> folder. This displays the contents of any items 
        previously imported. Double-click the title of the folder where the music files are located. 
        The files are listed in the middle window. You can now add files to the project using any of
        the methods described in the right side window.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Specifying Audio Files to Copy</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_035.png" format="PNG"
                         width="15cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>


      <step performance="required">
        <para>The selected files now appear in the project window. You can
        also view the estimated disc usage once these files are written to the
        disc at the bottom of the project window. Based on this data, you may decide 
        to add or delete some files from your current selection. Once you are sure of 
        the files to be copied to the disc, click the <emphasis role="strong">Burn</emphasis> 
        button to start writing the audio files from your
        computer to the CD.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Audio Files to Write to Disc</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_037.png" format="PNG"
                         width="15cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The Disc Burning Setup window allows you to change the Properties
        of the project.  You can select the <emphasis role="strong">Options</emphasis>
        checkbox to leave the disc open to add a data session later.
        Click the <emphasis role="strong">Burn</emphasis> button to
        begin writing the files to the disc.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Confirming the CD Writing</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_038.png" format="PNG"
                         width="8cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Brasero now starts writing the music files to the media disc.
        You can view the progress in the <emphasis
        role="strong">Burning Audio Disc</emphasis> dialogue box. This process
        may take some time depending on the size of the files to be written to
        disc. Once the process is complete, you have a new CD containing all
        your favourite songs.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Writing an Audio CD</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_039.png" format="PNG"
                         width="9cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Playing Proprietary Multimedia Formats</title>

    <para>As previously stated, due to the legal restrictions associated with
    the use of proprietary formats, Ubuntu does not offer support for such
    formats by default. If you wish to play proprietary formats, you will
    need to install additional multimedia codecs. A multimedia codec is a
    small piece of software that allows you to watch videos or listen to music
    of a specific format. Although Ubuntu includes many codecs by default, you
    may need to install more because there are many different multimedia
    formats and it is unrealistic to provide them all.</para>

    <para>Playback of multimedia files in Ubuntu is handled by the Gstreamer
    multimedia framework. GStreamer by itself does not provide any multimedia
    codecs, it relies on codecs that have been packaged into a <emphasis
    role="strong">plugin</emphasis> that it uses to perform the actual
    recording and playback.The easist way to install is to install the package 
    "ubuntu-restricted-extras".It also contains lots of other restricted softwares,which may be
    need a licenss. </para>

    <para>Other applications, such as VLC, MPlayer and Xine, do not use the
    Gstreamer framework.</para>

    <para>You can use the Synaptic Package Manager, or the Command Line
    Interface (CLI) to install these multimedia codecs available in the
    repositories.</para>

    <tip>
      <title>Nice to Know:</title>

      <para>Codecs can be installed directly from the Movie Player. When Movie
      Player recognizes a format it cannot play, it checks if a Gstreamer
      plugin is available for this format. If it finds one, you can install
      the codec easily without following the lengthy solution presented
      below.</para>
    </tip>

    <procedure>
      <title>To install a codec plugin using Synaptic Package Manager:</title>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">System</emphasis> menu, point to
        <emphasis role="strong">Administration</emphasis> and then click
        <emphasis role="strong">Synaptic Package Manager</emphasis>. The
        <emphasis role="strong">Synaptic Package Manager</emphasis> window
        opens.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The <emphasis role="strong">Multiverse</emphasis> and <emphasis
        role="strong">Restricted</emphasis> repositories are not activated by
        default in Ubuntu. To install the additional multimedia codecs, you
        need to first activate these repositories. On the <emphasis
        role="strong">Settings</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Repositories</emphasis>. The <emphasis
        role="strong">Software</emphasis> <emphasis
        role="strong">Sources</emphasis> dialogue box is displayed.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Displaying Software Sources</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_041.png" format="PNG"
                         width="15cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To enable the Multiverse and Restricted repositories, select the
        third and fourth check boxes available on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Ubuntu Software</emphasis> tabbed page, and click
        <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the dialogue
        box.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Enabling Repositories</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_042.png" format="PNG"
                         width="12cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>You may receive a notification that your repository information
        has changed. Click <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit
        this message.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Repositories Information Notification</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_043.png" format="PNG"
                         width="10cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Once you return to the Synaptic Package Manager window, you are
        required to click the <emphasis role="strong">Reload</emphasis> button
        to apply your changes.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Applying Changes</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_044.png" format="PNG"
                         width="15cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>On clicking the <emphasis role="strong">Reload</emphasis>
        button, the system starts checking the repositories for new, removed
        or upgraded software packages.</para>

        <figure float="0">
          <title>Checking Package Information</title>

          <mediaobject>
            <imageobject>
              <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_045.png" format="PNG"
                         width="10cm" />
            </imageobject>
          </mediaobject>
        </figure>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>After the Multiverse and Restricted repositories are added in
        the Ubuntu software sources, you can download and install additional
        multimedia codecs. To install a software package, you need to first
        locate the package in the Synaptic Package Manager window. You can
        either search for a specific software package manually or run a search
        using the search utility provided in the Synaptic Package Manager. To
        initiate a search for a specific package, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Search.</emphasis>,and begain to install 
        "ubuntu-restricted-extras" just like in lession 3.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
  </sect1>


  <sect1>
    <title>Creating and Editing Audio Files</title>

    <para>Ubuntu provides you with various tools to create your own music and
    audio files. The default application available in Ubuntu for creation of
    audio files is the GNOME Sound Recorder. Similarly, you can also edit
    audio files using Audacity.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Creating Audio Files</title>

      <para>Ubuntu provides you with tools to create new audio files using an
      input device such as a microphone. Sound Recorder is the default
      application available in Ubuntu for creating audio files.</para>

      <procedure>
        <title>To start recording audio using Sound Recorder:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu,
          point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and
          then click <emphasis role="strong">Sound Recorder</emphasis>.
          </para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Launching Sound Recorder</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_059.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Sound Recorder allows you to record and play .flac, .ogg,
          and .wav audio files. You can also select the audio quality and formate 
          from the <emphasis role="strong">Record as</emphasis>
          drop-down list.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting the quality and formate</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_060.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Before starting the recording, it is advisable to configure
          the volume control settings to derive quality audio output. To
          access the volume controls, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">File</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Open Volume Control</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Accessing Volume Controls</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_061.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You use the slider buttons on the tracks to set the volume
          control for all the audio input and output devices. To further
          specify your volume preferences, click Preferences on the Edit menu.
          This opens the <emphasis role="strong">Volume Control
          Preferences</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Displaying Volume Preferences</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_062.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
        
        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can use the <emphasis role="strong">input</emphasis> 
          tab to setting the input preferences.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Input tab</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_063.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You are returned to the <emphasis role="strong">Sound
          Recorder</emphasis> window. Now, you can start recording the audio
          from the selected input device by clicking the <emphasis
          role="strong">Record</emphasis> button. The recording starts.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Recording Sound</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_064.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>After the recording is complete, you can play the recorded
          sound file by clicking the <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis>
          button. The progress indicator moves along the progress bar as the
          sound file is playing. You can also view the duration of the
          recorded file in minutes and seconds under the <emphasis
          role="strong">File information</emphasis> section.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing Recorded Sound File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_065.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Editing Audio Files</title>

      <para>You can use Audacity for editing audio files. Audacity is
      not included in the default installation of Ubuntu but it is a free and
      open source software application, which can be installed easily from the
      Universe repository of Ubuntu. You can install
      Audacity using either the Add/Remove Applications or the Synaptic
      Package Manger.</para>

      <procedure>
        <title>To edit audio files using Audacity:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu,
          point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and
          then click <emphasis role="strong">Audacity Sound
          Editor</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Launching Audacity</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_066.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The Audacity main interface window is displayed. You can use
          the various controls and tools to play,
          create and edit audio files.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Audacity Window</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_068.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can now start editing an existing audio file in Audacity.
          To do so, you need to first import the audio file into Audacity. To
          import an audio file, on the <emphasis role="strong">File</emphasis>
          menu, point to <emphasis role="strong">Import</emphasis> and then
          select <emphasis role="strong">Audio</emphasis>. The <emphasis
          role="strong">Select one or more audio files</emphasis> dialogue box
          opens.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Importing Audio Files into Audacity</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_069.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Select the audio file that you want to edit and click
          <emphasis role="strong">Open</emphasis> to open the file in
          Audacity.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting the Files to Import</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_070.png"
                           format="PNG" width="11cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The selected audio file opens in the Audacity interface. The
          audio file is represented as the blue waves in the lower part of the
          Audacity window. Now you can perform a whole range of tasks on this
          file.You can cut off some unwanted portion of the imported audio
          file, insert silence at some point, can add various audio effects on
          different sections of the file and may even export the file into an
          altogether different file format.</para>

          <para>Audacity also allows you to play an audio file.
          Click the <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis> button to start
          playing the audio file.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing the Imported File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_071.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The audio file starts playing in the Audacity audio editor.
          You can use the various tools available with Audacity to start
          editing the current audio file:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Magnifying tool: If you find that due to the length of the
              current file, you are unable to view the portions that you want
              to edit, you can use the Magnifying tool. This will let you zoom
              in on a specific area.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Envelop tool: This enables you to change the volume of
              specific selections of the sound file.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Time Shift tool: Allows you to move the entire sound file
              in relation to time; helpful when you are working with multiple
              tracks.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Selection tool: Enables you to highlight portions of the
              sound file on which you want to work.</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>To start editing a specific portion of the sound file,
          activate the <emphasis role="strong">Selection</emphasis> tool by
          clicking it.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Picking the Selection Tool</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_072.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Select the area you wish to edit by dragging across the area
          while pressing the left mouse button. The selected area appears in a
          shade of darker gray.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting Audio Portion to Edit</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_073.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can now cut the area if you wish to remove this part of
          the audio file otherwise, edit this portion by applying various
          sound effects to it. The Effect menu contains all the digital audio
          effects that you can apply on an audio file. Some of these
          are:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Amplify - Increases or decreases volume without altering
              sound quality</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>BassBoost - Increases the volume of a specific
              frequency.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Echo - Allows you to add an echo specify the delay
              time.</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Fade in - Fades from silence to the present volume</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Fade out - Fades from present volume to silence</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Invert - Flips the audio samples upside down</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Noise Removal-Allows you to remove background noise</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Reverse - Allows you to play the selection backward</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>

          <para>To increase the volume of the selected portion, on the
          <emphasis role="strong">Effect</emphasis> menu, select <emphasis
          role="strong">Amplify</emphasis>. The <emphasis
          role="strong">Amplify</emphasis> window opens.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Applying Sound Effects</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_074.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Amplify</emphasis> window, you
          can use the slide bar to increase or decrease the amplification.
          Click OK to apply the effect to the selected portion of the
          audio.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Amplifying the Audio Clip</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_075.png"
                           format="PNG" width="9cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Notice that the blue waves in the selected area have changed.
          You can now listen to the changed audio by clicking the <emphasis
          role="strong">Play</emphasis> button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Verifying the Edit Effects</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_076.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>After you are satisfied with all the edit effects, you can
          save the edited audio file. Because the default audio format of
          Audacity is not readily supported by many applications you should
          save the file in a more popular audio format, such as Ogg Vorbis or
          MP3.</para>

          <para>To save the file in a different file format, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Export</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Exporting Audio File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_077.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Export File</emphasis> dialogue
          box, select the folder where you want to save the file. Then, select
          the desired file format from the drop-down list and then click
          <emphasis role="strong">Save</emphasis> to export the file in the
          specified file format.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Exporting as MP3 File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_078.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Audacity starts exporting the file in the specified file
          format. This process may take up some time depending on the length
          of the audio file.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Export Progress Indicator</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_079.png"
                           format="PNG" width="9cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <para>The audio file is exported to the specified location. You can
          now close the Audacity window and listen to the edited audio file
          whenever you wish.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Playing DVDs</title>

    <para>Most commercial DVDs are encrypted with the Content Scrambling
    System (CSS), which attempts to restrict the sotware that can play a DVD.
    By default, Ubuntu is capable of playing DVDs that are not encrypted. 
    Due to legal restrictions surrounding the CSS format, as well as
    Ubuntu's commitment to free multimedia formats, some software
    packages needed for encrypted DVD playback are not installed by default in
    Ubuntu. You can install these packages from Ubuntu repositories to enable
    the playback of encrypted DVDs.</para>

    <note>
      <title>Note:</title>

      <para>It is possible that the use of some of the following software to
      play or copy DVDs is not permitted by law in some countries. Please
      check your rights before proceeding.</para>
    </note>

    <para>You may also consider downloading the following additional
    applications that are capable of playing certain formats by
    default:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para>Mplayer movie player</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>VLC media player</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Xine</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Totem-xine</para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>

    <para>Totem Movie Player, the default movie player included in Ubuntu can
    automatically play a DVD when it is inserted into the DVD drive. However,
    it will not provide access to the DVD menu. Other free software media
    players like VLC, mplayer and xine do make the DVD menu available.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Playing DVDs in Totem Movie Player</title>

      <para>After you have installed all the required software packages from
      various Ubuntu repositories, you can play a DVD on your Totem movie
      player.</para>

      <procedure>
        <title>To play a DVD on Totem:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Insert the DVD in the DVD drive of your computer. This will
          automatically launch the Totem and the DVD will start
          playing.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Playing a DVD in Totem</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_080.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>To view the DVD in full screen mode, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">View</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Fullscreen</emphasis>. Alternatively, you can simply
          press <emphasis role="strong">F</emphasis> on your keyboard.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Enabling the Full Screen View</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_081.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can enjoy the DVD in full screen mode or press <emphasis
          role="strong">ESC</emphasis> and return to the Totem window.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Viewing DVD in Full Screen</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_082.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13.5cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Totem also allows you to configure some settings to view the
          DVD according to your preferences. To configure the preferences
          settings, on the <emphasis role="strong">Edit</emphasis> menu, click
          <emphasis role="strong">Preferences</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Displaying Totem Configuration</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_083.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can use the Preferences dialogue box to define various
          display settings, such as the brightness, colour, hue and saturation
          of the display. After specifying your preferences, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the dialogue box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Customising Display Settings</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_084.png"
                           format="PNG" width="11cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>When watching a DVD, you can use the various options provided
          in the <emphasis role="strong">Go</emphasis> menu to navigate inside
          the DVD. To skip to the next frame, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">Go</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis role="strong">Skip
          Forwards</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Navigating Inside a DVD</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_085.png" format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You are taken to the next frame in the DVD. If you do not want
          to view the side bar when playing the DVD, click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Sidebar</emphasis> button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Hiding the Sidebar</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_086.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Viewing the DVD</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_087.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>This hides the side bar and now you can view the DVD on a
          larger space and simultaneously, have all the playback controls
          right in front of you.</para>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Backing up DVDs</title>

      <para>If you have a collection of old and not-so-easy-to-find DVDs, you
      may wish to back up these on your computer or create extra copies of
      them. You may even want to extract certain tracks from your DVD and
      watch it later. To do so, Ubuntu provides you with a number of DVD
      backup applications or DVD rippers. Although these applications are not
      included in Ubuntu by default, you can download and install them from
      the Ubuntu repositories. Some of these applications are: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Thoggen</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>K9copy</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>dvd::rip</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>HandBrake</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <note userlevel="instructor">
        <title>Instructor Notes:</title>

        <para>If the students want to know more about the above applications,
        advise them to visit the following Web pages: For dvd::rip- <ulink
        url="http://www2.exit1.org/dvdrip/">http://www2.exit1.org/dvdrip/</ulink>
        For K9copy- <ulink
        url="http://k9copy.sourceforge.net/">http://k9copy.sourceforge.net/</ulink>
        For HandBrake- <ulink
        url="http://handbrake.m0k.org/?chapter=documentation">http://handbrake.m0k.org/?chapter=documentation</ulink>.</para>
      </note>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Backing up DVDs Using Thoggen</title>

        <para>Thoggen is a DVD backup utility for Linux, based on GStreamer
        and Gtk+. This application is designed to be easy-to-use. Rather than
        exposing the complexities of the DVD ripping process, which many other
        applications tend to do, it tries to simplify the process for average
        users by offering sensible default options.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <para>Thoggen includes certain key features: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>Is easy to use and has a nice graphical user interface
            (GUI)</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Supports title preview, picture cropping, and picture
            resizing</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Provides language Selection for audio track</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Encodes into Ogg/Theora video</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Can encode from local directory with video DVD files</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>Is based on the GStreamer multimedia framework, which makes
            it fairly easy to add additional encoding formats/codecs in
            future.</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

      <note>
        <title>Note:</title>

        <para>Thoggen should work just fine for the most part, but make still sure to check the list of known issues. <ulink
        url="http://thoggen.net/download/index.html#known-issues">http://thoggen.net/download/index.html#known-issues</ulink>.</para>
      </note>

      <para>To be able to back up your DVD using Thoggen, you need to first
      install it. You can easily find this application in the Universe
      repository of Synaptic Package Manager and install it on your
      computer.</para>

      <figure float="0">
        <title>Installing Thoggen</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_088.png" format="PNG"
                       width="15cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <procedure>
        <title>To start backing up your DVD using Thoggen:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu,
          point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and
          then click <emphasis role="strong">Thoggen DVD
          Ripper</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Launching Thoggen</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_089.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The <emphasis role="strong">Thoggen</emphasis> window appears.
          As a first step to backing up your DVD, it simply asks you to select
          the specific tracks on the DVD that you want to back up. Specify the
          tracks by selecting the corresponding check boxes and then click
          <emphasis role="strong">OK</emphasis> to proceed.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Specifying the Tracks to Back up</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_090.png"
                           format="PNG" width="9cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the next step of the backing up process, you are allowed to
          view and configure some of the settings according to your
          requirements. You can select the picture size from the corresponding
          drop-down list and define the output crop, by clicking the <emphasis
          role="strong">Configure Cropping</emphasis> button. Otherwise, you
          cam simply click <emphasis role="strong">OK</emphasis> to accept the
          default settings and continue with the process of backing up your
          DVD.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Changing Default Settings</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_091.png"
                           format="PNG" width="11cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The DVD backing process starts immediately. You can view the
          progress of the current as well as the entire process in the
          <emphasis role="strong">Progress</emphasis> section of the Thoggen
          window. Thoggen takes quite long to backup a DVD. However, the final
          output is of a very high quality.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Backing up DVD</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_092.png"
                           format="PNG" width="11cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Playing Online Media</title>

    <para>Ubuntu provides you with tools to directly play music and videos
    available on the Internet. You can listen and watch online videos and
    audios directly from within your browser but may require to install some
    special player for this. Your ability to watch or listen to online media
    depends on how the provider of the music and video has made them
    available.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Watching Videos in a Web Browser</title>

      <para>You can play many of the videos available on the Internet directly
      from within your browser. For example, You can watch the Google videos
      and the You Tube videos directly in your FireFox window without
      installing any special player or additional browser plugins. The
      following screenshot displays a video being played inside the Firefox
      window:</para>

      <figure float="0">
        <title>Watching Video in a Web Browser</title>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_093.png" format="PNG"
                       width="15cm" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>However, depending on the format of the video that you want to
      watch, you may also require to download and install certain additional
      browser plugins. Some of the plugins available for the default Firefox
      web browser are: <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Totem Xine plugin:</title>

              <para>Install the <emphasis role="strong">
              totem-xine-firefox-plugin</emphasis> package from the "Universe"
              repository.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Totem gstreamer plugin:</title>

              <para>Install the <emphasis role="strong">
              totem-gstreamer-firefox-plugin</emphasis> package from the
              "Universe" repository.</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Mplayer plugin:</title>

              <para>Install the <emphasis role="strong">
              mozilla-mplayer</emphasis> package from the Universe
              repository</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <formalpara>
              <title>Flash plugin:</title>

              <para>install the <emphasis role="strong">
              flashplugin-nonfree</emphasis> package from the "Multiverse"
              repository</para>
            </formalpara>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist></para>

        <tip>
            <title>Nice to Know:</title>

            <para>If you find that all Chinese characters can not display corretcly in flash,
            you can use this command to correct it:
            <emphasis role="strong">sudo rm /etc/fonts/conf.d/49-sansserif.conf</emphasis>.
            </para>
          </tip>

      <para>The plugin installation process depends on the framework you use.
      If you use Totem-gstreamer, the default movie player included in Ubuntu,
      you need to install the totem-gstreamer-firefox-plugin package. However,
      to enable playing streaming video in your browser, you need to first
      install the Microsoft Windows codec and then install the totem
      plugin.</para>

      <para>You can even install an additional mediaplayer, such as RealPlayer
      10, to watch online video streams in Realmedia formats. When you have
      installed all the above mentioned plugins and codecs, you can watch
      RealMedia files even with your default media player, such as Totem. But,
      you may also want to install RealPlayer on your computer because
      RealPlayer supports streaming RealMedia files slightly better than other
      players.</para>

      <para>The RealPlayer, developed by RealNetworks, supports a number of
      audio and video codecs such as realaudio, realvideo 10, mp3, ogg vorbis
      and theora, h263 and AAC. The RealPlayer for Linux is available in the
      Canonical commercial repository and can also be freely downloaded from
      the RealPlayer web site.</para>

      <note>
        <title>Note:</title>

        <para>RealPlayer is a proprietary software and is not supported by the
        Ubuntu community.</para>
      </note>

      <formalpara>
        <title>Installing RealPlayer</title>

        <para>As mentioned above, the realPlayer for Linux is available in the
        Canonical commercial repository. Ubuntu does not include this
        repository by default. Therefore, you will first need to add
        Canonical's commercial repository to your system. Once the repository
        is added, you can search for the Realplayer package and then install
        it on your computer.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <procedure>
        <title>Watching Online Videos Using RealPlayer</title>

        <para></para>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can now access the realPlayer from the Applications menu.
          To access RealPlayer, on the <emphasis
          role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu, point to <emphasis
          role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and then click <emphasis
          role="strong">RealPlayer 10</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Launching
            RealPlayer</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_094.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The <emphasis role="strong">RealPlayer Setup
          Assistant</emphasis> is displayed to guide you through the set up of
          the RealPlayer. Click <emphasis role="strong">Forward</emphasis> to
          start the set up process.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Initiating RealPlayer Set
            up</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_095.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>After reviewing the release notes of the RealPlayer 10, click
          <emphasis role="strong">Forward</emphasis> again to proceed.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Reviewing realPlayer Release
            Notes</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_096.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Before installing the RealPlayer application on your computer,
          you need to review the terms of the end user license agreement and
          accept it to be able to proceed with the setup. Click <emphasis
          role="strong">Accept.</emphasis></para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Accepting the License
            Agreement</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_097.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You have reached the final screen of the Realplayer setup
          Assistant. Specify the provided options and click <emphasis
          role="strong">OK</emphasis> to complete the set up.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Completing the Set-up
            Process</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_098.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The <emphasis role="strong">RealPlayer</emphasis> window is
          displayed, indicating that the set up was successful. Now you can
          watch online streaming media in the RealPlayer.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">The RealPlayer
            Window</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_099.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>To start viewing the online video of your choice, launch
          Firefox and navigate to the Web page from which you want to
          view the streaming media.</para>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the Web page, click the link to open the video of your
          choice.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Selecting the Link to the Online
            Video</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_101.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You are asked to specify whether you want to open the linked
          file in RealPlayer or save it to your computer. To view the video as
          online streaming media, accept the default selection and click
          <emphasis role="strong">OK</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Viewing Video as Streaming
            Media</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_102.png"
                           format="PNG" width="10cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The <emphasis role="strong">Downloads</emphasis> dialogue box
          displays the progress of the download. After the file is downloaded
          to your temporary Internet folder, the video starts playing in the
          <emphasis role="strong"> RealPlayer</emphasis> window.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Watching Online Video in
            RealPlayer</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_103.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You can add the link to your <emphasis
          role="strong">Favorites</emphasis> list to be able to view the video
          again without searching for it on the Internet. To save the video as
          a <emphasis role="strong">Favorite,</emphasis> on the the <emphasis
          role="strong">Favorites</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Add to Favorite</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Saving a Video as
            Favourite</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_104.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The video is now saved as your favorite. In future, you can
          view this video directly from inside your RealPlayer by selecting
          the link from the <emphasis role="strong">Favorites</emphasis> menu.
          You can also play an online video directly from inside the
          RealPlayer by specifying the location of the video. To do so, on the
          <emphasis role="strong">File</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
          role="strong">Open Location</emphasis>.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Viewing Online Video Directly from
            RealPlayer</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_105.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>Type the URL or the file path of the video in the <emphasis
          role="strong">Open Location</emphasis> dialogue box and click
          <emphasis role="strong">OK</emphasis> to start playing the online
          streaming video.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title><emphasis role="italic">Specifying Video
            Location</emphasis></title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_106.png"
                           format="PNG" width="8cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Editing Videos</title>

    <para>In addition to viewing movies and videos, Ubuntu also provides you
    tools to help you edit a video. The tools available with Ubuntu
    include:</para>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">Kino:</emphasis> An advanced video editor,
    Kino captures video to disk in Raw DV and AVI format. It allows you to
    load multiple video clips, cut and paste portions of video, and save it to
    an edit decision list in SMIL and XML formats.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">Stopmotion:</emphasis> Stopmotion is a free
    application for creating stop-motion animation movies. It enables you to
    create stop-motions from pictures imported from a camera or from the
    harddrive, add sound effects and export the animation to different video
    formats such as mpeg or avi.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">Subtitle Editor:</emphasis> Subtitle Editor
    is a GTK+2 tool to edit subtitles for movies and videos. you can use it
    for creating new subtitles or to transform, edit, correct and refine
    existing subtitles. This programme also shows sound waves, which makes it
    easier to synchronise subtitles to voices.</para>

    <para><emphasis role="strong">Pitivi Video Editor:</emphasis> Pitivi Video
    Editor is a non-linear editor, which allows you to easily edit audio and
    video projects. Using Pitivi, you can capture audio and video, mix,
    resize, cut, and apply effects to audio and video sources. It also allows
    you to save the projects in any format supported by the GStreamer
    framework.</para>

    <sect2>
      <title>Editing Videos Using Pitivi Video Editor</title>

      <para>Pitivi Video Editor is installed in Ubuntu by default.So you can use it right now.</para>

      <procedure>
        <title>To edit video using Pitivi Video Editor:</title>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Applications</emphasis> menu,
          point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and
          then click <emphasis role="strong">Pitivi Video Editor</emphasis>.
          The <emphasis role="strong">Pitivi</emphasis> window
          opens.</para>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The main Pitivi interface is divided into a number of panes.
          You can use the various buttons on the task bar to perform tasks
          such as opening, importing, adding, viewing and saving video clips.
          To edit a video clip, first import the clip in the Pitivi Video
          editor by clicking the <emphasis role="strong">Import
          Clips</emphasis> button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Pitivi Interface</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_107.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the Import a clip dialogue box, navigate to the folder from
          where you want to import the video clip, select the single or
          multiple clips to be edited and click <emphasis
          role="strong">Add</emphasis> to import it in the <emphasis
          role="strong">Pitivi</emphasis> window.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Importing Video Clips in Pitivi</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_108.png"
                           format="PNG" width="12cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The selected video clip is now imported into the Pitivi Video
          editor. You can double-click the video clip to view it in the right
          pane. Click the <emphasis role="strong">Stop</emphasis> button on
          the control bar to stop the playback.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Viewing the Imported Video</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_109.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>To edit the imported video clip, you need to drag them to the
          bottom pane to add them to the time line and then select the
          <emphasis role="strong">Project Settings</emphasis> option from the
          <emphasis role="strong">File</emphasis> menu. This opens the
          <emphasis role="strong">Projects Settings</emphasis> dialogue
          box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Displaying the Project Settings Dialogue Box</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_110.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Projects Settings</emphasis>
          dialogue box, you can edit the various aspects of the selected movie
          clip by defining various specifications according to your
          preferences. You can use the <emphasis role="strong">Video
          Output</emphasis> section to define the height, width and the frame
          rate of the video. Similarly, you can define the audio
          specifications under the <emphasis role="strong">Audio
          Output</emphasis> section. Click <emphasis
          role="strong">OK</emphasis> after specifying your
          preferences.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Specifying Edit Preferences</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_111.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>You return to the Pitivi window. To start applying your
          specifications on the selected video clip, click the <emphasis
          role="strong">Render project</emphasis> button. This displays the
          <emphasis role="strong">Render project</emphasis> dialogue box. You
          can use the <emphasis role="strong">Modify</emphasis> button on the
          <emphasis role="strong">Render project</emphasis> dialogue box to
          further modify your specifications for the video clip. Otherwise,
          click the <emphasis role="strong">Choose file</emphasis> button to
          specify a file name for the edited video clip.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Specifying the Output File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_112.png"
                           format="PNG" width="10cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>This opens the <emphasis role="strong">Choose file to render
          to</emphasis> dialogue box. Use this dialogue box to assign a name
          for the edited video clip and specify the location where you want it
          to be saved. After specifying these details, click <emphasis
          role="strong">OK</emphasis> to continue.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Selecting the File to Render to</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_113.png"
                           format="PNG" width="13cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The name of the file now appears on the <emphasis
          role="strong">Output file</emphasis> button. Start editing the video
          clip by clicking the <emphasis role="strong">Record</emphasis>
          button.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Editing the Video File</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_114.png"
                           format="PNG" width="10cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The Pitivi Video Editor has started rendering a new project
          based on your specifications. You can view the progress of the
          process in the progress bar. Once the rendering is complete, click
          the Close button on the top-right corner to exit the <emphasis
          role="strong">Render project</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>Project Rendering Progress Indicator</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_115.png"
                           format="PNG" width="10cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>

        <step performance="required">
          <para>The newly edited video clip is now saved at the specified
          location.</para>

          <figure float="0">
            <title>The Edited Video Clip</title>

            <mediaobject>
              <imageobject>
                <imagedata fileref="images/chapter9_image_116.png"
                           format="PNG" width="15cm" />
              </imageobject>
            </mediaobject>
          </figure>
        </step>
      </procedure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Lesson Summary</title>

    <para>In this lesson, you learned that: <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>Software usage and distribution is controlled by laws and
          legislations unique to each country.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>When using or redistributing proprietary media formats, you
          should be aware of the associated patent or copyright laws.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>You can use Rhythmbox to play and organise music, listen to
          Internet radio and import music from CDs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Using Sound Juicer, you can play audio tracks direct from the
          CD, extract audio tracks and convert them into audio files in
          various file formats. In addition, the default audio CD/DVD burner for
          Ubuntu, Brasero, can be used to create audio and data CD/DVDs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Playback of proprietary multimedia formats can be enabled in
          Ubuntu by installing additional multimedia codecs from the
          repositories.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Sound Recorder can be used to create audio files in
          various formats.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Audacity enables you to record and edit audio files.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>DVD playback in Totem Movie Player can be enabled by
          installing the required software packages.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Thoggen is a DVD backup utility for Linux that can be used in
          Ubuntu to copy DVDs.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Ubuntu provides you with tools to listen and watch online
          videos and audios directly from within your browser or in a
          mediaplayer such as RealPlayer.</para>
        </listitem>

        <listitem>
          <para>Pitivi video Editor can be used to play and edit
          videos.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist></para>
  </sect1>

  <sect1 role="questions">
    <title>Review Exercise</title>

    <qandaset>
      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>List the main features of a free software license.</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>A free software license include the following features:
          <itemizedlist>
              <listitem>
                <para>Enables anyone to distribute or sell the software</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Makes the source code of the software available</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Allows users to make modifications and to produce
                derived works</para>
              </listitem>

              <listitem>
                <para>Does not restrict the use of other software</para>
              </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Which is the default music player in Ubuntu?</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Totem</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Rhythmbox</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Audacity</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>gtkpod</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>b) Rhythmbox</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>What are podcasts?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Podcasts are audio shows, broadcasted over the Internet, that
          you can subscribe to. Subscribing to a podcast enables you to
          download each new audio release from the subscribed podcast
          source.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Which application is available in Ubuntu by default to play
          and extract audio compact discs?</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Xine</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>RealPlayer</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Brasero</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>Sound Juicer</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Sound Juicer</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>In which formats does Sound Juicer enable you to extract audio
          files onto your computer?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Sound Juicer enables you to extract audio files into the
          following three formats:</para>

          <itemizedlist>
            <listitem>
              <para>Ogg Vorbis</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>FLAC</para>
            </listitem>

            <listitem>
              <para>WAV</para>
            </listitem>
          </itemizedlist>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>From where does Sound Juicer retrieves retrieve the CD artist,
          title, and track data?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Sound Juicer will retrieve the CD artist, title, and track
          data from MusicBrainz.org.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Name the default CD audio recording application available in
          Ubuntu?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Brasero is the audio CD burner application that comes
          bundled with Ubuntu, by default.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>Why do you need to install additional multimedia codecs in
          Ubuntu?</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Due to the legal restrictions associated with the use of
          proprietary formats, by default, Ubuntu does not offer support for
          such formats. You need to install additional multimedia codecs to
          enabling such proprietary media formats in Ubuntu.</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>

      <qandaentry>
        <question>
          <para>You can download and install multimedia codecs using the
          ____________________.</para>
        </question>

        <answer>
          <para>Synaptic Package Manager or Command Line Interface</para>
        </answer>
      </qandaentry>
    </qandaset>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Lab Exercise</title>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Exercise 1: Playing Music Using Rhythmbox</title>

      <para>You have recently installed Ubuntu and want to play and organise
      your music files, listen to music podcasts and Internet radio. List the
      steps that you would take.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <orderedlist continuation="restarts" inheritnum="ignore"
                 numeration="arabic">
      <listitem>
        <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Application</emphasis> menu,
        point to <emphasis role="strong">Sound &amp; Video</emphasis> and then
        click <emphasis role="strong">Rhythmbox Music
        Player</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To start importing individual music files into Rhythmbox,
        right-click <emphasis role="strong">Library</emphasis> and click
        <emphasis role="strong">Import File</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Import File into
        Library</emphasis> dialogue box, navigate to the folder from which you
        want to import the files.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the files that you want to import and click <emphasis
        role="strong">Open.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Select the music tracks that you want to play and the <emphasis
        role="strong">Play</emphasis> button to start playing the selected
        track.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To play music from a podcast of your choice, right-click the
        <emphasis role="strong">Podcast</emphasis> option in the <emphasis
        role="strong">Library</emphasis> list and select <emphasis
        role="strong">New Podcast Feed</emphasis>.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Enter the podcast feed URL in the <emphasis role="strong">New
        Podcast Feed</emphasis> text box and click <emphasis
        role="strong">Add.</emphasis></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To play a podcast episode, select the episode that you want to
        play and click the <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis>
        button.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To listen to Internet radio, click the <emphasis
        role="strong">Radio</emphasis> source in the <emphasis
        role="strong">Library</emphasis> pane.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Double-click on the radio station of your choice to listen to
        the streaming media.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>To add a new radio station to the existing list of stations,
        click <emphasis role="strong">New Internet Radio Station</emphasis>
        and paste the URL of the new radio station in the <emphasis
        role="strong">URL of Internet radio station</emphasis> text
        box.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>Click <emphasis role="strong">Add</emphasis> to add the radio
        station in the existing list.</para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para>You can add many more Internet radio stations in the same way
        and listen to your favourite radio stations with just a click of your
        mouse.</para>
      </listitem>
    </orderedlist>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Exercise 2: Playing and Extracting Audio CDs</title>

      <para>You have built up an impressive CD collection over the years and
      you would like to play these on your Ubuntu desktop, retrieve details
      about the music tracks and extract your favourite music tracks onto your
      computer in a compatible format to be able to play them later. List the
      steps that you would need to perform to do all that you want.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <procedure>
      <title>To play audio CDs:</title>

      <para></para>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Insert an audio CD in the CD drive of your computer. The
        <emphasis role="strong">Sound Juicer</emphasis> CD player and ripper
        is launched automatically.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Notice that <emphasis role="strong">Sound Juicer</emphasis> has
        fetched the tracks' information from MusicBrainz.org.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To play the tracks of your choice, select the particular tracks
        by selecting the corresponding checkboxes.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Click the <emphasis role="strong">Play</emphasis> button to play
        the tracks.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <procedure>
      <title>To extract an audio CD:</title>

      <para></para>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Insert the audio CD into your computer's CD drive.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">Edit</emphasis> menu, click
        <emphasis role="strong">Preferences.</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue
        box, click the <emphasis role="strong">Output Format</emphasis>
        drop-down list.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Select the format of your choice from the <emphasis
        role="strong">Output Format</emphasis> drop-down list.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Select the directory where you want to extract the files from
        the <emphasis role="strong">Music Folder</emphasis> drop-down
        list.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Click <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the
        <emphasis role="strong">Preferences</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Sound Juicer</emphasis> window,
        select the tracks that you want to extract by selecting the
        corresponding check boxes.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Click the <emphasis role="strong">Extract</emphasis> button to
        start extracting the files.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Sound Juicer notifies you after the selected tracks are
        extracted successfully. Click <emphasis role="strong">Open</emphasis>
        to view the tracks copied on your hard disk.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The CD audio tracks are now copied as audio files on your hard
        disk. You can listen to these tracks by simply double-clicking
        them.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Exercise 3: Burning Audio CDs</title>

      <para>You have recently discovered a Web site from where you can freely
      download hundreds of songs. You do not want these files to occupy the
      precious space on your computer's hard drive. Therefore, you want to
      copy these files on audio CDs, so that you can listen to them in future
      without taking up space on the hard drive.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <procedure>
      <title>To burn an audio CD:</title>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Insert a blank (recordable) CD in the CD drive of your
        computer.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Click the click the <emphasis role="strong">Make Audio
        CD</emphasis> button. This launches the <emphasis
        role="strong">Brasero Disc Burning</emphasis> application.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Click the 
        <emphasis role="strong">New Audio Project</emphasis> button.</para>
      </step>
      
      <step performance="required">
        <para>Navigate to the desired folder with the files you wish to add
        to display its contents.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Select the specific audio files that you want to be copied and
        click the <emphasis role="strong">Add</emphasis> button or simply drag 
        each file name to the Files area in the right side of the project window.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Once you are sure of the files to be copied to the disk, click
        the <emphasis role="strong">Burn</emphasis> button to start
        writing the audio files from your computer to the CD.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The Disc Burning Setup dialogue box displays.
        Click <emphasis role="strong">Burn</emphasis> to
        continue.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Brasero now starts writing the music files to the media disc.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Exercise 4: Playing Proprietary Multimedia formats</title>

      <para>You have a huge collection of music in MP3 format stored on your
      computer and want to play these music files on your Ubuntu desktop. List
      the steps that you will need to take to be able install the required
      multimedia codecs.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <procedure>
      <title>To Install a codec plugin using Synaptic Package Manager:</title>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>On the <emphasis role="strong">System</emphasis> menu, point to
        <emphasis role="strong">Administration</emphasis> and then click
        <emphasis role="strong">Synaptic Package Manager</emphasis>. The
        <emphasis role="strong">Synaptic Package Manager</emphasis> window
        opens.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The Multiverse and Restricted repositories are not activated by
        default in Ubuntu. To activate these repositories, on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Settings</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Repositories.</emphasis> The <emphasis
        role="strong">Software Sources</emphasis> dialogue box is
        displayed.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To enable the Multiverse and Restricted repositories, select the
        third and fourth check boxes available on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Ubuntu Software</emphasis> tabbed page, and click
        <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the dialogue
        box.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>You may receive a notification that your repository information
        has changed. Click <emphasis role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit
        this message.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Once you return to the Synaptic Package Manager window, you are
        required to click the <emphasis role="strong">Reload</emphasis> button
        to apply your changes.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>On clicking the <emphasis role="strong">Reload</emphasis>
        button, the system starts checking the repositories for new, removed
        or upgraded software packages.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To install a software package, you need to first locate the
        package in the Synaptic Package Manager window.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To initiate a search for a specific package, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Search.</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>In the <emphasis role="strong">Search</emphasis> field, enter
        the name of the software package that you are looking for. Click
        <emphasis role="strong">Search</emphasis> to begin the search.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Right-click the package to be installed and select <emphasis
        role="strong">Mark for Installation</emphasis>.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Once all the required packages are marked, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Apply</emphasis> to start downloading the packages. The
        <emphasis role="strong">Summary</emphasis> dialogue box is
        displayed.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To go ahead with the marked installations, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Apply</emphasis> on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Summary</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>After all the mark software packages are downloaded and
        installed, the <emphasis role="strong">Changes Applied</emphasis>
        dialogue box is displayed. Click <emphasis
        role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the <emphasis
        role="strong">Changes Applied</emphasis> dialogue box.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>The check box corresponding to the recently installed software
        package has changed to green, indicating that the software has been
        installed successfully.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>

    <formalpara>
      <title>Exercise 5: Playing DVDs</title>

      <para>One of your friends has recently given you a DVD gift box set of
      your favourite movies of all times. Now, you want to play this DVD in
      your Ubuntu desktop and enjoy your favourite movies.</para>
    </formalpara>

    <procedure>
      <title>To play the DVD in the Movie player:</title>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Install the following software packages from the Universe and
        Multiverse repositories using the Synaptic Package Manager.</para>

        <itemizedlist>
          <listitem>
            <para>gxine</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>libdvdcss2</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>libdvdnav4</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>libdvdplay0</para>
          </listitem>

          <listitem>
            <para>libdvdvread3</para>
          </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Install the Ubuntu Restricted Extras software package from the
        Ubuntu repository.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>Insert the DVD into the DVD drive of your computer. This will
        automatically launch the Totem and the DVD will start playing.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To view the DVD in full screen mode, on the View menu, click
        Fullscreen. Alternatively, you can simply press F on your
        keyboard.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>You can enjoy the DVD in full screen mode. At any point of time,
        while watching the DVD in fullscreen mode, you can press ESC and
        return to the Totem window.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To configure the preferences settings, on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Edit</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Preferences.</emphasis></para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>After specifying your preferences, click <emphasis
        role="strong">Close</emphasis> to exit the dialogue box.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>To skip to the next frame, on the <emphasis
        role="strong">Go</emphasis> menu, click <emphasis role="strong">Skip
        Forwards</emphasis>.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>You do not want to view the side bar when playing the DVD, click
        the <emphasis role="strong">Sidebar</emphasis> button.</para>
      </step>

      <step performance="required">
        <para>This hides the side bar and now you can view the DVD on a bigger
        space and simultaneously, have all the playback controls right in
        front of you.</para>
      </step>
    </procedure>
    </sect1>
</chapter>
